Luc Blassel

PhD Student, interested in Machine learning in Biology

☑ luc.blassel@gmail.com @ lucblassel.com

Paris, France

I am a PhD student in computational biology at the Institut Pasteur in France. I started with biology studies in AgroParisTech, a Parisian "Grande école" but quickly found my way to machine learning. In order to complete my M.Sc, I entered the Institut Pasteur as an intern, and found the fascinating world of academic research.

I have since continued on, entering a PhD program in computational biology, exploring the interface between biology, computer science and machine learning.

This interdisciplinary experience drives me to further explore computational methods to resolve problems of a biological nature.

Experience

Post-Doctoral Researcher, CNRS, Paris, France

2023-

During this postdoc I will work on the phyhloformer project with Laurent Jacob and members of the LBBE in Lyon. My work will center around improving the performacne of the model, making it's output closer to the real phylogenetic tree. I will also be adding funcitonality to the model, mainly the ability to take unaligned sequences as input.

PhD Student, Institut Pasteur, Paris, France

2020-2023

PhD in computational biology, focused on improving and learning from sequence alignments. With the ever growing quantity of high quality sequencing data, we are now able to develop methods to take advantage of this data. My PhD project followed 2 different axes: (1) Using machine learning to discover Drug resistance mutations in HIV (Continuation of the M.Sc project) (2) Search of a function space for sequence transformation functions that improve sequence mapping and alignment.

This PhD was supervized by Rayan Chikhi and funded by the PRAIRIE institute. The manuscript can be found here

Research Engineer, Institut Pasteur, Paris, France

2018-2020

Using machine learning and large datasets to explore the drug resistance landscape in HIV. Supervized by Olivier Gascuel. A large dataset of UK HIV sequences associated with patient RT-treatment status was used to train several machine learning algorithms. Examining the important learned features gave us insight in mutations associated to ART failure. This project resulted in a publication. Project page here, and M.Sc thesis (in french).

Data Scientist Intern, CapitalData, Paris, France

Mar-Sept 2017

As a data scientist intern at Capital data I was tasked with developing a software pipeline to validate data prior to database integration, and detect anomalies usign time series. This was implemented in R and Python. I also, developed reporting-oriented data visualizations of KPIs using BIME and Tableau. Finally statistical AB-testing was also done using python.

Teaching and tutoring, self-employed, Paris, France

2015-2022

Since the beginning of my higher education, I have beedn tutoring middle school, high school and university students in scientific subjects, mainly mathematics. The aim is to turn the students into independents people, more confident in their abilities and more knowledgeable in order to excel in their respective studies.

Since Septemeber 2021, I have been doing oral examination in English for PCSI preparatory class students as the ENCPB in Paris, France.

Education

Masters of Science (M.Sc.), Dep. MIDO, Dauphine université, France

2017-2018

during the IASD program, I followed courses in Deep learning, reinforcement learning, statistical modelling, software engineering and data science. This was a double curriculum with the AgroParisTech IODAA program.

Diplôme d'Ingénieur, AgroParisTech, Paris, France

2014-2018

The first two years of this programm are focused on biology with courses in molecular biology, ecology, health, epidemiology and statistics.

During the final year, I followed the IODAA program, which was done as a double curriculum with Duaphine université, studying machine learning, data science and statistical modelling with a focus on biological problems.

2 year French preparatory class to prepare a nationally ranked exam for entry in the "Grande Écoles" ranked 201/1967 (Veto), ranked 481/2991 (Agro)

Languages

Other languages¹

Mandarin Chinese³

Mother tongue French & English

Understanding				Speaking					Writing
Listening		Reading		Interaction		Production			
B1	Independent	В1	Independent	В1	Independent	В1	Independent	В1	Independent
A2	Basic	A2	Basic	A2	Basic	A2	Basic	A2	Basic

Common European Framework of Reference for Languages (CEFR)

Publications (Google scholar, ORCID)

German²

Journal articles

Mapping-friendly sequence reductions: Going beyond homopolymer compression

Luc Blassel, Paul Medvedev, Rayan Chikhi

iScience 25.11, p. 105305 DOI: 10.1016/j.isci.2022.105305

Using Machine Learning and Big Data to Explore the Drug Resistance Landscape in HIV

Luc Blassel, Anna Tostevin, Christian Julian Villabona-Arenas, Martine Peeters, Stéphane Hué, Olivier Gascuel PLOS Computational Biology 17.8, e1008873

DOI: 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1008873

Drug Resistance Mutations in HIV: New Bioinformatics Approaches and Challenges

Luc Blassel, Anna Zhukova, Christian J Villabona-Arenas, Katherine E Atkins, Stéphane Hué, Olivier Gascuel Current Opinion in Virology 51, pp. 56-64

DOI: 10.1016/j.coviro.2021.09.009

Origin, Evolution and Global Spread of SARS-CoV-2

Anna Zhukova, Luc Blassel, Frédéric Lemoine, Marie Morel, Jakub Voznica, Olivier Gascuel

Comptes Rendus. Biologies 344.1, pp. 57-75

DOI: 10.5802/crbiol.29

COVID-Align: accurate online alignment of hCoV-19 genomes using a profile HMM

Frédéric Lemoine, Luc Blassel, Jakub Voznica, Olivier Gascuel

Bioinformatics (btaa871)

DOI: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btaa871

Conference talks

Mapping-Friendly Sequence Reductions: Going beyond Homopolymer Compression

Luc Blassel, Paul Medvedev, Rayan Chikhi

RECOMB-SEQ 2022

² 1 month program at Goethe Institute in Schwäbisch Hall, Germany

³ 5 month program at SISU Shanghai, Chian & 1 month program at UIR, Beijing, CN